<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Declaration and apology of the Protestant people that is, of the noblemen, barrons, gentlemen, burgesses, and commons of all sorts, now in armes within the kingdom of Scotland.</title>
            <author>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, Earl of, 1629-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3677</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230114</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896187</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75567)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2380:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Declaration and apology of the Protestant people that is, of the noblemen, barrons, gentlemen, burgesses, and commons of all sorts, now in armes within the kingdom of Scotland.</title>
                  <author>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, Earl of, 1629-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed more exactly then formerly conform to the true copye,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Declaration, And APOLOGY of the PROTESTANT PEOPLE That is, Of the Noblemen, Barrons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, and Commons of all ſorts, Now in Armes within the Kingdom of Scotland.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL LXVIII. V. 1. 2.</bibl> Let God ariſe; let his enemies be ſcattered; let them alſo, that hate him, flee before him; as ſmoke is driven away, ſo drive them away; as wax melteth before the fire, ſo let the wicked perish at the preſence of God.</q>
            <p>Reprinted more exactly then formerly conform to the True Copye.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153806:2"/>
            <head>The Declaration, and Apology of the Proteſtant People; That is of the Noblemen, Barrons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, And Commons of all ſorts, now in Armes within the Kingdom of Scotland, with the concurrence of their true and faithful Paſtors, and of ſeveral Gentlemen of the English Nation, joyned with them in the ſame cauſe; For defence and releif of their Lives, Rights, &amp; Liberties, and recovery and reeſtablishment of the true Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in behalfe of them ſelves, and all that shall Joyn with, and adhere to them.</head>
            <p>They muſt be altogether ſtrangers, or very litle concerned in the <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> who (after all that <hi>the Nations and Churches about</hi> have Seen, of the Lords mighty hand and ſtreatched-out arm in the late <hi>wars</hi> betuixt <hi>King Charles the Firſt.</hi> and his <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Parliaments of Scotland, England &amp; Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Againſt the then Conſpyreings of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> to the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty;</hi> The wonderful advancement of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> within theſe Kingdomes, that therupon enſued: With the general <hi>refreshment, joy,</hi> and <hi>ſecurity</hi> of all the Proteſtant Churches abroad, that thence redounded: And the no leſs rooted and firm <hi>Loyalty</hi> of the ſame people, who notwithſtanding of their long bloody and fatal <hi>contendings</hi> with the <hi>father,</hi> Did Yet upon reaſonable fair and juſt <hi>treaties,</hi> concluded with all the aſſurance, that either <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion honour</hi> or <hi>gratitude</hi> could promiſe, call back and reſtore <hi>Charles the 2d. his ſone</hi> to his thron and empire) Are not fully convinced and ſatisfied, that conſidering the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual contradictings and counteractings of all <hi>theſe</hi> ſacred and ſolemn <hi>engadgments</hi> that imediatly and ever ſince have been practiſed; the whole reign of the aforſaid <hi>Charles the 2d.</hi> (through the ſiniſtrous and ſubtile influences of a <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>popish party,</hi> now manifeſtly diſcovered) <hi>was</hi> a conſtant &amp; uniform courſe of <hi>perjury apoftacy,</hi> and <hi>violence: Begun</hi> with open <hi>rebellion</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> The <hi>reſcinding,</hi> not only of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>lawes,</hi> but, by an un-paralled moſt un-politick and pernicious device, of whole un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exceptionable <hi>parliaments,</hi> for the ſpace of tuenty ſeven yeares preceeding, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding both our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> were therein expreſly, legally and well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for; and the cruel <hi>ſhedding</hi> of the beſt Proteſtant <hi>blood,</hi> in the moſt unjuſt execution of the <hi>Late Marquis of Argyll,</hi> and many other <hi>worthies,</hi> contrar to all Law and reaſon: <hi>Carried</hi> on by the <hi>ſmiting</hi> and <hi>caſting out</hi> of more faithfull and pious <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> and <hi>ſcattering</hi> and <hi>diſſipating</hi> more true <hi>flockes</hi> and <hi>followers</hi> of Chriſt, than was done in moſt of the <hi>ten primitive perſecutions,</hi> and the <hi>diludgeing</hi> of theſe Lands with all villanous <hi>debauchries</hi> and <hi>abominable licentiousneſs,</hi> to the very <hi>profligating</hi> of <hi>conſcience morality</hi> and <hi>common honeſty</hi> from among men: <hi>And</hi> thence forward <hi>accomplished</hi> by a moſt un-relenting <hi>perſecution,</hi> and <hi>appreſſion</hi> of the generality of Gods people in their <hi>conſciences, Perſons</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſtates,</hi> with <hi>vexations</hi> and <hi>rigours</hi> almoſt incredible, and that for no other reaſon, but becauſe they could not <hi>actively</hi> comply with theſe notorious <hi>Perfidies.</hi> and the manifold <hi>profanations</hi> and <hi>miſcheifs,</hi> where with they are attended.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>hellish myſtery</hi> of <hi>Antichriſtian iniquity and arbitrary Tyranny, impoſing</hi> upon many <hi>at home</hi> too willing, through their love of eaſe, to be abuſed and <hi>deluding</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant churches abroad</hi> (in that woefull and viſible <hi>indifferency,</hi> that every where reigns) by the <hi>vain</hi> pretext of the <hi>mere notion</hi> of our <hi>courts</hi> empty and ſimulat
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153806:2"/> proteſtant profeſſion, having of a long time under the <hi>late King</hi> made moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>advances</hi> in the following particulars, and many <hi>more</hi> that might be enumerated, all too evidently <hi>ſeen,</hi> and heavily felt, to need any explicite proof or demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</p>
            <p>As 1. not only in the abovementioned open and avowed <hi>revolting</hi> from God, by breach of <hi>Sworn treaties, Covenants,</hi> and <hi>coronation oaths,</hi> and <hi>ſlighting</hi> and <hi>deſpiſcing</hi> ſpontaneous <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>proclamations,</hi> the <hi>overturning</hi> the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and <hi>ranverſing</hi> at one blow our beſt and moſt legal eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The <hi>ungrate</hi> as well as <hi>unjuſt putting to death</hi> of moſt innocent and faithful men, upon abſurd <hi>pretences:</hi> convelled by the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>cuſtoms</hi> of nations, and in the time of Gods greateſt <hi>indulgence</hi> towards the authors; The <hi>deſolating</hi> of the <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>changing</hi> of the <hi>ordinances of God,</hi> for <hi>ſetting up</hi> the frivolous and ſuperſtitious <hi>inventions of men,</hi> the <hi>countenancing</hi> and <hi>encouraging</hi> of all <hi>vice</hi> and <hi>profanity,</hi> and the violent and griveous <hi>perſecuting</hi> of all conſcience and <hi>conſcientious</hi> men.</p>
            <p>But nixt and more particularly, in the <hi>conniving</hi> at <hi>Papiſts</hi> their <hi>meetings</hi> and <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous maſſes,</hi> while in the mean time all <hi>Proteſtant Nonconformiſts</hi> are perſecuted with endleſs <hi>ſeverities:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>raiſing of ſtanding forces,</hi> the very <hi>bane</hi> of all <hi>civil</hi> and <hi>Lawful Government,</hi> and that without any <hi>other meaſure,</hi> ſave what the <hi>indigence</hi> of Court <hi>Luxury</hi> and <hi>profuſion</hi> did neceſſarly <hi>put</hi> unto it:</p>
            <p>The <hi>declaring</hi> and <hi>appointing</hi> all <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Officers,</hi> to enjoy their places <hi>only during pleaſure,</hi> on purpoſe to make them more <hi>ſouple</hi> and <hi>complyant</hi> to all their <hi>maſters</hi> deſignes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>abuſing</hi> of the <hi>great truſt</hi> of <hi>calling</hi> and <hi>diſſolving</hi> Parliaments, the <hi>moſt high</hi> and <hi>neceſſary courts</hi> of the Kingdomes, by iniquous <hi>Packing,</hi> unſeaſonable <hi>proroguing,</hi> pernicious <hi>diſcharging,</hi> and inſolent <hi>baffling</hi> them <hi>at pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>exalting</hi> of the Kings <hi>ſupremacy,</hi> under the colour of his pretended <hi>right</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> about the <hi>external Government</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to an expreſs and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut power, of <hi>enacting</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtatuting</hi> in all <hi>Church meetings</hi> and <hi>matters,</hi> as he in his wiſdom ſhall think fitt; a ready &amp; prepared <hi>tool</hi> to bring us back not only to <hi>Popery</hi> but to <hi>Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſtrange perverſion</hi> of the <hi>high truſt</hi> of the <hi>Militia,</hi> committed to his Majeſty expreſſy, for the <hi>protection</hi> of <hi>good ſubjects,</hi> and the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of all our <hi>proteſtant friends abroad,</hi> only to the <hi>invading</hi> and <hi>oppreſſing</hi> by lawleſs <hi>hoſts</hi> of the worſt of <hi>high landers</hi> and <hi>low landers,</hi> in times of profound <hi>peace,</hi> the beſt <hi>parts</hi> of the Kingdom, purpoſly to ruin them, becauſe <hi>too Proteſtant,</hi> by <hi>free quarter</hi> and other illegal <hi>exactions</hi>' and <hi>the making warr</hi> moſt <hi>cauſleſly</hi> and <hi>obſtinatly</hi> againſt the <hi>States of the united Neitherlands,</hi> our <hi>beſt</hi> nighbours, and the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> bulwarck of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> intereſt:</p>
            <p>The <hi>forcing</hi> of <hi>poor people,</hi> by the extream <hi>rigours</hi> of exorbitart <hi>finings, impriſonings, beatings ſtigmatizins, ſpoilings, banishments,</hi> and other <hi>violences,</hi> for the ſimple <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> to take <hi>armes</hi> in their own <hi>defence</hi> as at <hi>Pentland</hi> and <hi>Bothwel bridge</hi> and then <hi>demeaning</hi> and <hi>executing</hi> them, what in <hi>fields</hi> what on <hi>ſcaffolds,</hi> as the <hi>moſt deſperat</hi> of traitours, and at the ſame time <hi>involving</hi> whole <hi>countryes</hi> upon the moſt <hi>ſlender</hi> and <hi>abſurd pretexts,</hi> of inevitable <hi>intercommunings</hi> and <hi>reſet,</hi> both in their <hi>crimes</hi> and <hi>punishments:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſetting up</hi> of the moſt <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>obnoxious</hi> of men, to be <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Law, and <hi>Packing juries,</hi> and <hi>aſſizes</hi> moſt partially, for their worſt ends:</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſtraining, ſtreaching,</hi> and <hi>wreaſting</hi> of Law, not only in <hi>prejudice</hi> of every one ſuſpected to be <hi>diſſaffected</hi> to their evil courſes but the <hi>violation</hi> of all right, for <hi>ſpoiling,</hi> and <hi>robbing cities</hi> and <hi>incorporations</hi> of their ancient and undoubted <hi>priviledges,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153806:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>tranſporting</hi> of <hi>freemen</hi> as <hi>ſlaves</hi> to <hi>forreine</hi> plantations, for not <hi>making faith</hi> to anſwer (againſt law) <hi>ſuper inquirendis,</hi> as alſo for <hi>not dilating</hi> men upon <hi>Oath</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a moſt impious <hi>Law</hi> lately made againſt <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi>) in <hi>matters</hi> where in the <hi>party</hi> put to <hi>ſwear,</hi> judges them to be in their <hi>duty,</hi> &amp; without <hi>exception</hi> of his <hi>neareſt relations;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>arbitrarie impriſonings</hi> and <hi>detainings of free ſubjests</hi> without either bringing them to <hi>trial,</hi> or allowing them any <hi>hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>torturing</hi> of ſeveral perſons, even <hi>fyve times</hi> more, of <hi>conſcientious non confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> within theſe <hi>tuenty</hi> yeares, then of all ſorts of <hi>fellons</hi> and <hi>malefactors</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> theſe <hi>hundered</hi> yeares by paſt, and that without either <hi>juſt previous grounds,</hi> regarding of <hi>Legal methods,</hi> or obſerving the <hi>meaſures</hi> of <hi>common humanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>eliciting</hi> by promiſes of <hi>indemnity,</hi> and the <hi>publick faith</hi> interpoſed for that effect <hi>voluntary confeſſions</hi> of ſome as of <hi>Mr. Iames Mitchill</hi> &amp;c. and then not only <hi>retracting,</hi> and <hi>diſſowning</hi> the <hi>promiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>condition</hi> upon <hi>Oath,</hi> in face of the juſtice court, but further <hi>witneſſing</hi> the <hi>confeſſion</hi> to the poor mans <hi>condemnation:</hi> not with ſtanding the <hi>bookes of council</hi> containing the aforſaid <hi>indemnity</hi> were produced and <hi>laid open</hi> before and at the very time of their <hi>ſwearing;</hi> Lyke as of Late after moſt <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>exquiſit tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> practiſed upon <hi>Mr. Spens</hi> &amp; <hi>Mr. Carſtairs,</hi> and a <hi>full</hi> &amp; <hi>ample promiſe</hi> there after made them with <hi>an act</hi> upon it, that neither <hi>they</hi> nor their <hi>evidence</hi> should ever be made uſe of to <hi>their</hi> or to any <hi>other</hi> mens hurt; they never the leſs cauſe <hi>produce</hi> and do <hi>ſuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine</hi> Mr. Carſtairs <hi>depoſition</hi> Againſt <hi>Bailzie of Iarviſwood</hi> for an <hi>adminicle</hi> or <hi>aid</hi> to their lame and defective <hi>probation;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>making</hi> men <hi>offenders</hi> yea <hi>traitours for words,</hi> and theſe <hi>true fair</hi> and <hi>innocent;</hi> As the <hi>Earl of Argyl,</hi> for <hi>declaring</hi> before the <hi>Council</hi> after <hi>leave given,</hi> and with <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and only for <hi>exonering</hi> his own conſcience that <hi>he believed, the Parliament intended no contradiction in the teſt, and therefore was willing to take it in their ſens viz: for ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion, and that he did not thereby mean to bind up him ſelf from endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lawfully in Church and State, what Religion and Loyaltie might obleidge and allow him to do,</hi> for which <hi>words</hi> nevertheleſs he was <hi>tryed</hi> and <hi>condemned as a traitour,</hi> in the <hi>loſs</hi> of his <hi>life, lands,</hi> and <hi>goods;</hi> and ſtands <hi>de facto deprived</hi> of both <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>goods,</hi> having only ſaved his <hi>life</hi> in the <hi>extremitie</hi> by a gracions providential <hi>eſcape</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cruel <hi>executing</hi> to the <hi>death</hi> of ſeveral <hi>hundreds</hi> within theſe <hi>tuenty</hi> yeares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſids <hi>many hundreds</hi> more, that have either <hi>fallen</hi> in the <hi>fields,</hi> or been made to, <hi>perish</hi> in their <hi>impriſonments,</hi> or <hi>tranſportations,</hi> and that for the alone <hi>cauſe</hi> or on the <hi>occaſion</hi> of their <hi>conſcientious non conforming.</hi> And ſome of them (of which <hi>number</hi> ſeveral <hi>poor women</hi>) for their <hi>bare opinion</hi> about the Kings <hi>breach of truſt,</hi> never before by them <hi>vented,</hi> but ſimply <hi>declared</hi> upon <hi>examination,</hi> and <hi>moſt part</hi> of them <hi>diſpatched</hi> with that <hi>barbarous</hi> inhumanity as that (after no better <hi>example</hi> then that of the <hi>bloody Duke of Alba</hi>) they were by <hi>beating of Drumms</hi> hindered to ſpeak to the people their <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>dying words;</hi> And ſome of them, <hi>contrair</hi> to the perpetual cuſtom of <hi>Scotland</hi> and all the <hi>formes</hi> uſed in the <hi>Chriſtian world.</hi> and as if it had been on deſign <hi>to deſtroy</hi> both their <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>bodies, tryed ſentenced</hi> and <hi>put to death</hi> in <hi>one Day,</hi> yea the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>hour</hi> of their Death <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> concealed from them, that they might be <hi>cut of</hi> by a <hi>more mortal</hi> ſurpriſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>condemning</hi> ſome to <hi>death,</hi> others to the <hi>boring</hi> of their <hi>tongues,</hi> and <hi>ſyning</hi> many in moſt <hi>exorbitant</hi> ſummes even to 100000 <hi>pound Sterling,</hi> for <hi>calling</hi> the <hi>Duke of Yorke</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>notoriety</hi> of the matter to all men and <hi>his recuſancie ſound</hi> and <hi>declared</hi> by a <hi>grand jurie,</hi> and <hi>expreſſly Suppoſed</hi> by an <hi>exception</hi> in his favours, contained in an <hi>Act of parliament,</hi> and that now he <hi>goes</hi> openly to the <hi>maſs,</hi> and <hi>marches</hi> in <hi>ſolemn proceſſions</hi> to the <hi>horrour</hi> of all good <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſubjects:</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153806:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>looſing</hi> and <hi>exempting</hi> the <hi>Kings Sones</hi> and <hi>brothers,</hi> from what themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved to be the <hi>beſt fence</hi> and <hi>greateſt ſecuritie</hi> for the <hi>Proteſtant religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>impoſing</hi> and <hi>preſſing of Oaths without Law</hi> manifeſtly <hi>contradictorie,</hi> and that by <hi>terrible menacings, violent beatings, rigorous impriſonings</hi> and <hi>irreligious ſwearings,</hi> no leſs <hi>barbarous</hi> then what was practiſed by the <hi>Spanjards</hi> in <hi>Chriſtianiſing</hi> the <hi>wilde In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>eating up</hi> of men by <hi>free quarters,</hi> or otherwiſe <hi>falling on</hi> them by dounright <hi>violence,</hi> as <hi>dryving</hi> with <hi>drawen Swords,</hi> to conſtrain them to hear, whom in their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> they judged <hi>unſent</hi> and <hi>uncalled Curats,</hi> to the <hi>effaceing</hi> of all <hi>conſcience</hi> and <hi>oppen ſcorn</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and that <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>free religion,</hi> which he only accepts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>compelling</hi> the <hi>heritors of Shires</hi> to <hi>aſſeſſe</hi> them ſelves and the free ſubjects within their bounds, a <hi>thing</hi> expreſly <hi>denyed</hi> by Law to <hi>the King himſelf,</hi> and only <hi>reſerved</hi> to <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Sorning upon, harraſſing</hi> and <hi>deſtroying</hi> the beſt parts of the <hi>Country</hi> by <hi>four ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary circuits</hi> upon one and the ſame <hi>ſubject</hi> of <hi>Bothwel bridge,</hi> on purpoſe as it were to juſtify his <hi>highneſs</hi> judgment to his late <hi>majeſty. That it would not be well with Scotland untill the South of Forth</hi> (the better and more ſubſtantial halfe of that Kingdom) <hi>were turned to a hunting field.</hi> And to <hi>verify</hi> the <hi>late Chancellor</hi> the Earl of Aberdeen his <hi>affirmation</hi> at the <hi>Council board, that there was not a loyal ſubject weſt ward of the Caſtle of Edinburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>induſtrious ſtifling hindering</hi> or <hi>eluding</hi> the detection of all <hi>popish plots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Shamming</hi> of <hi>Mock plots</hi> upon good <hi>Proteſtants:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſuborning of witneſſes, hounding out</hi> and <hi>encouraging</hi> of <hi>Aſſaſſins</hi> to murder and cut the throats of honeſt men.</p>
            <p>And generally <hi>in the ſtudied</hi> and <hi>conſtant enſnaring</hi> or <hi>ruining</hi> upon every <hi>Shaddow</hi> of pretence all eſteemed either <hi>fixed</hi> to the <hi>proteſtant intereſt</hi> or <hi>well affected</hi> to their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries libertie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>wicked myſterie,</hi> wee Say, and <hi>conſpiracy</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyrranny</hi> inſeparablie <hi>twiſted</hi> both in experience and reaſon in all their <hi>attempts</hi> upon theſe <hi>great</hi> and <hi>mighty Nations</hi> ſo unanimouſly united and firmly fixed in their <hi>contrarie Profeſſion, rights &amp; liberties,</hi> having made ſo great a <hi>progreſs</hi> by the <hi>ſteps</hi> abovementioned, is now at length <hi>evidently diſcloſed</hi> and <hi>brought to full maturity</hi> by the moſt <hi>ſuſpicious</hi> (though with all <hi>moſt ungrate) cutting off</hi> of the <hi>late King</hi> as having indeed very unhappily acted all that part of which the <hi>conſpirators</hi> did judge him capable. <hi>The aſcending</hi> of <hi>James Duke of York</hi> a <hi>notorious apoſtat</hi> and <hi>bigot Papiſt</hi> to <hi>the throne,</hi> notwithſtanding his being <hi>thrice excluded</hi> by the <hi>Commons of England.</hi> And that he neither <hi>hath given</hi> nor <hi>can give</hi> without an <hi>hypocritical</hi> and <hi>damning cheat</hi> repugnant to his <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>contemptible</hi> to all ingenuous men <hi>the oath</hi> and <hi>ſecurity</hi> indiſpenſably required of him <hi>before,</hi> and <hi>at his entrie</hi> to the government. I 6. P. 1. c. 8. <hi>The approaching</hi> of two <hi>Parliaments,</hi> both <hi>called</hi> by him, <hi>one</hi> in Scotland, by his own vigilant <hi>Providence</hi> (in <hi>procureing</hi> it to be <hi>enacted</hi> in the <hi>laſt Parliament</hi> held by him in that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> That for the future not only <hi>all members of Parliament,</hi> but alſo <hi>all their electors</hi> should take that <hi>contradictorie</hi> and <hi>irreligions oath</hi> commonly called <hi>the Teſt,</hi> which no man owning <hi>conſcience,</hi> or <hi>careing</hi> for <hi>any religion</hi> can poſſibly approve) long ſince <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> for all <hi>his pleaſure.</hi> And <hi>the other</hi> in <hi>England packt, caballed,</hi> and <hi>returned</hi> by all the <hi>arts</hi> and <hi>methods</hi> that either <hi>fraud</hi> or <hi>injuſtice</hi> could invent, to render it <hi>plyable</hi> to his <hi>intentions,</hi> and which no doubt he will <hi>cajoll</hi> with all the <hi>faire promiſes</hi> and <hi>Large offers of Laws,</hi> that can he deſired for ſecuring both the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and their <hi>liberties;</hi> Providing they will but <hi>give money,</hi> which anſwers all things, and will as aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly fruſtrat; and ranverſe all theſe <hi>vain cautions. The perſueing</hi> with indefatigable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153806:4"/> malice even without the bounds of the <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and in <hi>all forreign parts all honeſt men, eſcaped</hi> for their <hi>lives</hi> and that either by <hi>Publick addreſſes or privat violences:</hi> ſo that they are neceſſarly reduced to that fatal dilemma, <hi>either to do or dy. The entering into &amp; entertaining more cloſs correſpondences</hi> then at any time before, with <hi>popish Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> Eſpecially the <hi>King of France,</hi> a moſt <hi>notorious enemie</hi> both of the <hi>true religion</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> of mankind. And laſtly by all that may be already <hi>ſeen</hi> in the <hi>changes</hi> and <hi>alterations</hi> he hath lately made, and that for here-after may be <hi>apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> from <hi>a falſe</hi> and <hi>bloody Religion,</hi> alwayes breathing forth and practiſing <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>fagot, murders</hi> and <hi>maſſacres</hi> and, a <hi>provock'd and inraged mind,</hi> Poſſeſſing and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>moſt determined</hi> of Princes, unqueſtionably <hi>capable</hi> and <hi>ready</hi> to execut all theſe <hi>bloody cruelties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which things being all of them either palpable <hi>perverſions</hi> or utterly <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the true and great <hi>ends of government,</hi> rendering our <hi>common Wealth</hi> our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon calamitie,</hi> and <hi>him</hi> who pretends to be its <hi>protector</hi> its moſt <hi>hoſtile enemie.</hi> and conſequently <hi>importing</hi> no leſs then a <hi>totall diſſolution</hi> of all the <hi>bonds</hi> of Subjection which the <hi>rulers</hi> have firſt ſo wickedly broke and cut aſſunder; and <hi>the liberating</hi> and <hi>alloweng</hi> all diſtreſſed ſubjects, whither thoſe <hi>already</hi> overwhelmed by, or who may juſtly for <hi>hereafter</hi> fear to be involved in theſe <hi>miſeryes,</hi> that <hi>undoubted right</hi> and <hi>power</hi> which both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> with <hi>comon reaſon</hi> and the <hi>conſtant cuſtom</hi> of all <hi>Nations</hi> have given us, for <hi>recovering defending</hi> and <hi>maintaining</hi> our <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>liberties,</hi> and above all the <hi>ineſtimable bleſſing</hi> of our <hi>pure Religion,</hi> to the effect that the ſame <hi>pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> with our <hi>juſt rights</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> ſo valiantly aſſerted by <hi>our anceſtors</hi> may be by us faithfully tranſmitted to <hi>our poſterities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have been &amp; are <hi>obliged</hi> and <hi>conſtrained</hi> by <hi>extream neceſſity</hi> and <hi>for common ſafety (the ſuprem laws</hi>) To take up <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>neceſſary arms</hi> in the <hi>name &amp; fear</hi> of the Great God, and <hi>the confidence</hi> of his mercie and aſſiſtance for <hi>our own</hi> and <hi>our Countries releif</hi> from the aforſaid moſt griveous and intolerable <hi>Tyrannies</hi> and <hi>oppreſſions; The defence</hi> and <hi>reeſtablishment</hi> of the <hi>true and pure Chriſtian Religion,</hi> commonly called <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> in oppoſition to that <hi>Antichriſtian Roman Religion,</hi> commonly called <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtical,</hi> and <hi>the recovery</hi> and <hi>reeſtablishmene</hi> of all our <hi>juſt rights liberties</hi> and <hi>privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,</hi> according as wee Stand <hi>indiſpenſably obliged</hi> there to, both before God &amp; men; And that <hi>againſt</hi> the <hi>ſaid James Duke of Yorck</hi> and all other his <hi>accomplices,</hi> our moſt unnatural and wicked <hi>enemies and oppreſſours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſyring</hi> in the firſt place to be <hi>deeply humbled</hi> each of us before God, for our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>provocations,</hi> Eſpecially our <hi>falſe heartedneſs</hi> and <hi>unſteedfaſtneſs in, &amp; revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from</hi> our great and manifold <hi>engadgments</hi> to him, that alone have brought upon us all theſe <hi>ſad miſcheifes,</hi> earneſtly and with our whole hearts ſupplicating, that he would <hi>ceaſe from his anger, Cauſe his face to Shine upon us.</hi> and <hi>ſave us for his own names ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the nixt place <hi>declaring</hi> lyke as we hereby <hi>expreſly declare,</hi> that our ſincere and ſingle <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>deſignes</hi> in this our <hi>undertakeing,</hi> are, <hi>Firſt</hi> the <hi>reſtoring and ſetling of</hi> the foreſaid <hi>true reformed Proteſtant Religion</hi> in its <hi>power</hi> and <hi>puritie,</hi> and with ſuch a juſt <hi>comprehenſion</hi> of pure Chriſtian <hi>charitie,</hi> as may thorow the good hand of our God upon us be truly ſatisfieing to all that fear him, and love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity; <hi>Renouncing</hi> and <hi>deteſting</hi> as well <hi>impoſings</hi> as <hi>errours,</hi> in all <hi>matters of Conſcience,</hi> and truſting that after the many <hi>teaching</hi> experiences we have had, we shall be for here after preſerved from all unhappy miſſunderſtandings. But rather thorow the <hi>Spirit of truth love</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> graciouſly led into all the <hi>paths</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>2ly. The <hi>ſuppreſſion</hi> and <hi>perpetual excluſion</hi> of <hi>antichriſtian Popery</hi> with all its <hi>idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſuperſtitions and falshoods,</hi> as alſo its moſt <hi>bitter root</hi> and <hi>of ſpring prelacy,</hi> with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153806:4"/> its new and wicked <hi>head the ſupremacie,</hi> and all their <hi>abuſes,</hi> that ſo not only the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and work of God may be <hi>revived</hi> in theſe lands, but alſo all the Churches of Chriſt abroad thereby <hi>refreshed</hi> and ſtrengthened.</p>
            <p>And 3ly <hi>The reſtoring</hi> of all men to their <hi>juſt rights</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> eſpecally <hi>the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing</hi> of all ſufferers, whether unto <hi>blood or loſs of liberty</hi> and <hi>goods, the releif</hi> of ſuch who are in preſent diſtreſs, the <hi>removing</hi> of all oppreſſion, and <hi>eſtablishing</hi> ſuch righteous <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>methods of Government,</hi> as may be moſt for ſecuring <hi>of liberty</hi> and <hi>property</hi> with the greateſt <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>equalitie;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which things as wee purpoſe and hope to accomplish only thorough the <hi>preſence</hi> of our God with us, and his <hi>bleſſing</hi> upon us, So we are moſt willing and reſolved that they be all <hi>ſetled</hi> and <hi>perfected</hi> by a <hi>free full juſt and Sonveraign repreſentatife</hi> of all the <hi>preſent undertakers</hi> and ſuch as shall Hereafter ſincerly <hi>concurre</hi> and <hi>take part</hi> with us; and that in ſuch <hi>formes</hi> and <hi>wayes</hi> as God by his good providence can only moſt happily <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>conduct us</hi> unto? <hi>declaring</hi> and <hi>proteſting</hi> further, that ſince ſuch have been and are the manifeſt <hi>perfidy treachery</hi> and <hi>falshood</hi> of our <hi>adverſaries,</hi> not only in their <hi>treaties</hi> and <hi>Convenants</hi> but alſo in their <hi>pardons indemnities</hi> and <hi>indulgences,</hi> as that they leave no ground or tolerable aſſurance <hi>of faith</hi> and <hi>truſt</hi> to be given to them, we will never <hi>enter into</hi> any termes of <hi>Capitulation treaties</hi> or <hi>conditions</hi> with them, as to the <hi>great ends</hi> of this undertaking; but on the contrary <hi>proſecut</hi> the ſame with all <hi>reality conſtancie</hi> and <hi>vigour</hi> without any <hi>ſeparation diviſion or backdrawing,</hi> untill they be perfectly and finally obtained. Upon which grounds and for which ends abovemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned we not only hereby moſt ſincerely and firmly <hi>proteſt</hi> and <hi>declare as in the preſence of God, conſtantly</hi> and <hi>perpetually</hi> to aſſiſt and maintain one another to the <hi>uttermoſt againſt all, deadly.</hi> But do more-over freely and heartily <hi>reſolve</hi> and <hi>engadge</hi> our ſelves to <hi>countenance</hi> and <hi>concurr</hi> with all our perſecuted and oppreſſed <hi>bretheren</hi> and <hi>freinds</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Irland,</hi> who from the <hi>Like</hi> reaſons and motives shall be induced and ſtirred up to <hi>the like</hi> undertaking for the <hi>ſame</hi> or the <hi>like</hi> Ends.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we moſt ſeriouſly and humbly <hi>beſeech and obteſt</hi> in the <hi>bowels of our lord I Chriſt</hi> all that love his <hi>truth</hi> and this our righteous <hi>cauſe,</hi> nonne excepted, though ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther formerly litle <hi>concerned for, &amp; favourable</hi> to us &amp; theſe intereſts, or even ſtill <hi>in actual oppoſition</hi> againſt us and them (their <hi>ſincere repentance</hi> being at all times to God moſt <hi>acceptable</hi> and not to be better <hi>witneſſed</hi> before men then by a contrarie and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>amendement) to come and joyn</hi> with us for <hi>Gods Glory,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> our <hi>country, lives rights</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> and our <hi>poſterities,</hi> and <hi>all our hope, Againſt</hi> an <hi>apoſtat Papiſt, an uſurping</hi> and <hi>perſecuting Tyran,</hi> by the moſt ſacred article of his Religion, our <hi>mortal enemy</hi> under the <hi>pain</hi> of his own <hi>Damnation,</hi> and by the <hi>fundamental and expreſs laws,</hi> of the land I. 6. P. 1. c. 9. &amp; P. 20. c. 5. incapable of the <hi>meaneſt office</hi> within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in effect a <hi>declared enemy</hi> and <hi>rebell</hi> I. 6. P. 3. c. 47. And who even by the Act lately made by himſelf for pathing the way to his ſucceſſion Ch. 2. p. 3. c. 2. can have no <hi>shaddow of pretence</hi> to the benefite thereof. Unleſs he firſt inſtruct him ſelf both to be the <hi>Lawfull and the immediat and neareſt heir of the croun,</hi> which without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfieing the old Law. Ia. 6. p. 1. c. 8. at the ſame time <hi>ratified</hi> Ch. 2. p. 3. c. 1. by <hi>ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to</hi> embrace and maintain the <hi>true reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> he can never poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie be, as was then diſtinctly underſtood, and declared by the principal <hi>framers</hi> of that Act. And <hi>againſt</hi> his <hi>adherents</hi> and <hi>pertakers,</hi> a perjured revolted and ſelf condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned generation. Upon whom the Lord, who will not give his <hi>glory</hi> to another, hath formerly got him ſelf <hi>a name and renoun</hi> before all the Nations, whom our <hi>ſins</hi> only have <hi>exalted,</hi> and whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> can never endure or their <hi>hands</hi> be ſtrong when the <hi>Lord</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> who is on our ſide, and hath a <hi>perpetual indignation</hi> againſt all the <hi>wicked</hi> in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153806:5"/> earth shall <hi>ariſe,</hi> and <hi>deal</hi> with them. And this our moſt earneſt <hi>call</hi> and <hi>requeſt</hi> we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently hope shall be the more readily hearkened unto, and heartily and ſeriouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with, that in the iſſue, thorow the <hi>bleſſing of God,</hi> it aſſuredly promiſes not only the <hi>reſtitution</hi> of <hi>truth, proſperity</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> to theſe long <hi>miſgoverned haraſſed and diſgraced Nationes:</hi> but the <hi>ſure defence</hi> and <hi>protection</hi> of <hi>true Religion</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> every where (Brittains certain and great <hi>intereſt</hi> of late moſt shamefully <hi>abandoned</hi>) and even the <hi>depreſſion</hi> of Antichriſt and the <hi>advancement</hi> and <hi>exaltation</hi> of the Kingdom of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in all the earth.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore be of good courage, and play the men for our people and for the cauſe of our God. And the Lord do that, which Seemeth him good.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>THE <hi>DECLARATION of ARCHIBALD Earl of ARGYLE, Lord</hi> Kintyre, Cowall, Campbel <hi>and</hi> Lorn, <hi>Heritable Sheriff and Lieutenant of the Shires of</hi> Argile <hi>and</hi> Tarbett, <hi>and Heritable Juſtice General of the ſaid Shires, and of the Weſt Iſles, and others. With his Order to his Vaſſals and others in the ſaid Shires, and under his Juriſdiction, to Concurr for Defence of their Religion, Lives and Liberties.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I shall not mention my <hi>Caſe,</hi> published in Print in Latine and more largely in English, nor mean I to repeat the Printed <hi>Declaration</hi> emitted by ſeveral Noblemen, Gentlemen, and others of both Nations now in Arms, but becauſe the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of me and my Family are therein mentioned, I have thought it fit for me, <hi>to declare</hi> for my ſelf; That as I go to <hi>Arms</hi> with thoſe who have appointed me to Conduct them, for <hi>no private,</hi> nor <hi>perſonal end,</hi> and only for <hi>thoſe</hi> contained in the ſaid <hi>Declaration,</hi> which I have concerted with them and approve of, ſo I <hi>do claim</hi> no intereſt, but what I had before the pretended <hi>Forfeiture</hi> of my Family, and have ſufficient right to.</p>
            <p>And that I do <hi>freely,</hi> (and as <hi>a Chriſtian</hi>) forgive all Perſonal Injuries againſt my Perſon or Family to all, that shall not oppoſe, but Join and Concur with us in our pre, ſent <hi>Undertaking,</hi> for the ends mentioned in the ſaid <hi>Declaration.</hi> And hereby I <hi>oblidge</hi> me never to <hi>purſue</hi> them in <hi>Iudgement;</hi> nor <hi>out of Iudgment;</hi> And I do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>declare,</hi> That obtaining the peaceable and quiet Poſſeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of what belonged to my Father and my ſelf before our pretended <hi>Forfeitures. I shall ſatisfie</hi> all Debts due by my Father and my ſelf, as any <hi>Heir</hi> or <hi>Debitor</hi> can be obliged.</p>
            <p>And as my <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> to his late Majeſty and his Government, hath ſufficiently appeared to all unbiaſſed Perſons, void of Malice, ſo I do <hi>with Grief acknowledge</hi> my former too much <hi>complying</hi> with, and <hi>connyving</hi> at the <hi>methods</hi> that have been taken to bring us to the ſad condition we are now in, though God knows never concurring in the <hi>deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now with Gods ſtrength ſuffered patiently my <hi>unjuſt Sentence</hi> and <hi>Banishment</hi> three years and a half, and have never offered to make any Uproar or defence by Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to diſturb the Peace upon my private Concern; But <hi>the King</hi> being now <hi>Dead,</hi> and <hi>the Duke of York</hi> having taken off his Mask, and having <hi>abandoned</hi> and <hi>invaded</hi> our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberties; <hi>Reſolving</hi> to enter into the Government and Exerciſe it <hi>contrary to Law;</hi> I think it not only <hi>Juſt,</hi> but <hi>my Duety</hi> to God and my Country, to uſe my outmoſt endeavors to oppoſe and repreſs his <hi>Uſurpation</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there fore being aſſiſted and furnished <hi>very nobly</hi> by ſeveral good Proteſtants, and invited and accompanied by ſeveral of both Nations to lead them, I <hi>reſolve,</hi> as God shall enable me, to uſe their aſſiſtance of all kinds, towards <hi>the ends</hi> expreſt in the ſaid <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I do hereby <hi>earneſtly invite</hi> and <hi>obteſte</hi> all honeſt Proteſtants, and particularly all my <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Blood Relations, to concur</hi> with us in the ſaid <hi>Declaration;</hi> And as I have written ſeveral Letters, ſo having no other way fully to intimate my mind otherwiſe, I do <hi>hereby require</hi> all my <hi>Vaſſals</hi> any where, and all within my ſeveral <hi>Juriſdictions with</hi> their <hi>Fencible Men</hi> within their <hi>Command,</hi> to go to Arms, and to join and concur with us according to the ſaid Declaration, as they will be anſwerable on their peril; And that they obey the particular <hi>Orders</hi> they shall receive from me from time to time.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
